Finding Aid for Walter E. Lay Papers, 1889-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Walter E. Lay Papers, 1889-1993
Lay, Walter Edwin.
9667 AA 2
Professor of Mechanical Engineering at the University of Michigan, 1915-1958, with emphasis in the area of automotive engineering and design; papers document his research, teaching and consulting activities.
2 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
These papers were donated by Shirley Lay Quimby (Donor No. 8353 in April 1995 and in July 1995.
This collection is open to research.
Walter E. Lay was born in Fulton, Michigan on February 5, 1889. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1915 with a degree in Mechanical Engineering. He began teaching in the Department of Mechanical Engineering later that year. Professor Lay was a pioneer in the area of automobile streaming and he wrote the "bible" on seat design. He had extensive contacts in the automobile industry and spent several summers in research and experimental capacities at Chevrolet, General Motors, Packard and the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics. His activities lead directly to the growth and development of the Automotive Engineering Laboratory now known as the Walter E. Lay Auto Lab. He became a full professor in 1930 and was named director of the lab. Professor Lay retired from the university in 1958. He was granted emeritus status in 1959. After his retirement from the university he remained interested in automotive design issues and also pursued interests in physics and chemistry. He moved to East Lansing in 1972 and died on August 28, 1974.
This collection is divided into six series:
Building and Space Concerns
Examinations
Lecture Notes
Personal
Problem Sets
Research
Visual Materials.
The Walter E. Lay papers include examinations; lecture notes; problem sets; research files; files relating to the building and expansion of the department of mechanical engineering and the Automotive Engineering Laboratory; and visual materials.
Subject:
Lay, Walter Edwin.; University of Michigan. Automotive Engineering Laboratory.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering.
Subject- Visual Materials:
Automobiles--Design and construction.; Laboratories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Automotive Engineering Laboratory.; Walter E. Lay Automotive Laboratory (University of Michigan); Lay, Walter Edwin.
Form and GenreTerms:
Photographs.
- Building and Space Concerns
  Building and Space Concerns contains information on the expansion needs and plans for the Department of Mechanical Engineering and in particular the Automotive Engineering Laboratory from 1919 to 1945.
  - "Automotive Division of the Mechanical Laboratory Proposed Layout" 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - "Automotive Laboratory Equipment, Space etc.," 1919 (Box 1)
  - Untitled 1928-1936 (Box 1)
  - Untitled 1943-1945 (Box 1)
- Examinations
  The Examinations series contains Professor Lay's copies of bluebooks and final exams given from 1935 to 1958. This series is arranged by course number and by date.
  - ME 14 1935-1938 (Box 1)
  - ME 60 1940-1945 (Box 1)
  - ME 114 1950-1958 (Box 1)
  - ME 150 1951-1958 (Box 1)
  - ME 155 1947 (Box 1)
  - ME 160 1946 (Box 1)
- Lecture Notes
  The Lecture Notes series includes notes and handouts from Professor Lay's classes, 1934 to 1960. This series is arranged by course number.
  - History of the Automobile 1947-1964 (Box 1)
  - ME 3 undated (Box 1)
  - ME 150
    - 1947-1964, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Clutch Transmission, Axles Steering, Brakes, Performance Maintenance 1941-1956 (Box 1)
    - Fuels Carburetor, Lubricant Bearings 1934-1955 (Box 1)
    - History, Statistics and Materials 1939-1951 (Box 1)
    - Schedules 1950-1956 (Box 1)
  - ME 155
    - Engine Tests 2-12 undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Engine Tests 1-13 1945-1958, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - General Handouts 1952-1957 (Box 2)
    - Instrumentation 1956-1960 (Box 2)
    - Schedules 1949-1958 (Box 2)
- Personal
  Information not directly relating to Lay's teaching and research is kept in the Personal series. This includes some alumni material for the class of 1915. It also includes some citations and awards Lay received. There is some material collected by the Lay family after his death that recognized his accomplishments. The series spans the years from 1915 to 1993.
  - Clippings 1956-1983 (Box 2)
  - Class of 1915
    - Correspondence 1955-1965 (Box 2)
    - Directories 1915-1965 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1957-1973 (Box 2)
  - Fiftieth Wedding Anniversary 1965 (Box 2)
  - Honors
    - Citation from College of Engineering 1969 (Box 2)
    - Dedication of Walter E. Lay Auto Lab 1976 (Box 2)
  - History 1957 (Box 2)
  - Obituary and Condolences 1974 (Box 2)
  - Programs 1953-1993 (Box 2)
  - Rogue's Gallery 1952 (Box 2)
- Problem Sets
  Problem Sets contains the answers to assignments in Lay's courses. This series is arranged by the course number.
  - ME 114
    - Untitled 1953-1958, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Chapter 1-17 1950-1957, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - ME 150 1954-1958 (Box 2)
- Research
  The Research series relates to Professor Lay's areas of interest but are not tied directly to his teaching activities. The series spans the period 1917-1964.
  - Acceleration Tests 1961 (Box 2)
  - Electric Car 1959-1961 (Box 2)
  - Gas Turbines 1960-1964 (Box 2)
  - Heat to Electric Power 1953-1959 (Box 2)
  - Published Work 1921-1968 (Box 2)
  - Report on the Doble Steam Power Plant 1917 (Box 2)
  - Streamlining of Automobiles 1917-1960 (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  Visual Materials is divided into two subseries: Photographs and Scrapbooks. The Photographs subseries (1917-1976) contains images from throughout Lay's career. Some prints are also included from the posthumous renaming of the auto lab in Lay's honor. Scrapbooks (1889?-1976) includes two bound volumes that illustrate the principal events in Lay's life.
  - Photographs, 1917-1976
    - Untitled undated (Box 2)
    - Auto Lab 1950-1959 (Box 2)
    - Auto Lab Bus 1932-1958
      - Auto Lab Equipment (Box 2)
      - Undated (Box 2)
      - 1961 (Box 2)
    - Class Reunions 1955-1965 (Box 2)
    - Construction of Auto Lab 1954-1958 (Box 2)
    - Dedication of Walter E. Lay Auto Lab 1976 (Box 2)
    - Road Tests
      - Undated (Box 2)
      - 1917-1958, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1889-1976
    - Untitled 1917-1958, 1 volumes (Volume 1)
    - "This is your life Walter E. Lay" circa 1889-1976, 1 volumes (Volume 2)
Related Material:
Walter E. Lay was a friend and colleague of Jay A. Bolt. The researcher is referred to the Jay A. Bolt collection for more information.